[
    {
        "question": "During facing operation in a conventional lathe the cutting velocity 46 mm",
        "options": [
            "Increases with feed",
            "Decreases with feed",
            "Unrelated to feed",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Unrelated to feed",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "On a lathe, you change settings in the machine to double the rotational speed of the spindle. This will also",
        "options": [
            "Double the feed (mm/rev) of the tool",
            "Halve the feed (mm/rev) of the tool",
            "Not affect the tool feed (mm/rev) at all",
            "Depends on whether the feed is longitudinal (mm/rev) or cross feed (mm/rev)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Not affect the tool feed (mm/rev) at all",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one is not a cutting tool material?",
        "options": [
            "High speed steel",
            "Tungsten carbide",
            "Stainless steel",
            "Ceramic"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stainless steel",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is not true in case of CNC machining centre (Milling).",
        "options": [
            "Machining is performed by writing a code in the computer",
            "3D (complex) surfaces can be machined",
            "Many types of operations can be performed in a single setup of workpiece",
            "It cannot be used for non-metallic materials."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It cannot be used for non-metallic materials.",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Feed used in thread cutting usually has the following relation with feed used in straight turning.",
        "options": [
            "Higher",
            "Equal",
            "Lower",
            "Unrelated"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lower",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In up milling operation,",
        "options": [
            "direction of rotation of cutter is same as direction of table movement",
            "direction of rotation of cutter is opposite to direction of table movement",
            "there is no such relation between directions of cutter and table movement",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "direction of rotation of cutter is opposite to direction of table movement",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "A job of diameter 100 mm is being turned using a cutting speed of 30 m/min. The corresponding feed is",
        "options": [
            "0.1 mm/rev",
            "10 mm/min",
            "300 \u03bcm",
            "not known"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "0.1 mm/rev",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Minimum number of axis in CNC turning centre (Lathe) and CNC machining centre (Milling) respectively are",
        "options": [
            "2 and 3",
            "3 and 3",
            "3 and 2",
            "4 and 4"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "2 and 3",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "A perfect square on the end of a round shaft can be milled by mounting it on",
        "options": [
            "A differential",
            "A compound rest",
            "An index plate",
            "A dividing head"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A dividing head",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The arbor of the milling machine is used to hold",
        "options": [
            "Spindle",
            "Cutting tool",
            "Workpiece",
            "Mandrel"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cutting tool",
        "week": 0,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is correct in context of miniaturization?",
        "options": [
            "Low accuracy and sensitivity",
            "High cost to performance ratio",
            "Faster device",
            "High energy required for excitation"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Faster device",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is MCU?",
        "options": [
            "Mechanical Control Unit",
            "Mechanical Central Unit",
            "Machine Control Unit",
            "Machine Central Unit"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Machine Control Unit",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a hybrid machining process?",
        "options": [
            "ECM",
            "EDM",
            "LBM",
            "ECDM"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "ECDM",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a material removal process?",
        "options": [
            "Forming",
            "Welding",
            "3D Printing",
            "Grinding"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Grinding",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The feature tolerance of an object is 0.001mm and its size is 10 mm, then its relative accuracy will be",
        "options": [
            "0.01",
            "10^4",
            "10.001",
            "10^-4"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "10^-4",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Most widely used workpiece material in MEMS based process is",
        "options": [
            "Steel",
            "Silicon",
            "Copper",
            "Aluminum"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Silicon",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Tool used in ultra-precision machining is",
        "options": [
            "WC",
            "HSS",
            "Natural Diamond Tool",
            "CBN"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Natural Diamond Tool",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a high production rate process?",
        "options": [
            "Mechanical micro machining",
            "MEMS based processes",
            "Ultra precision machining",
            "Additive manufacturing processes"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "MEMS based processes",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following path is a 3D machining or movement? (A \u2013 Starting point and D \u2013 Target point)?",
        "options": [
            "A\u2014G\u2014D",
            "A\u2014B\u2014D",
            "A\u2014F\u2014D",
            "A\u2014D"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A\u2014D",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Machine tool feedback device gives information of",
        "options": [
            "Position and velocity",
            "Cutting temperature",
            "Condition of cutting tool",
            "Vibration"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Position and velocity",
        "week": 1,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Small things are less affected by",
        "options": [
            "Mass",
            "Inertia",
            "Heat Storage",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (b)",
            "Only (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Surface tension is scaled with length at",
        "options": [
            "l^3",
            "l^2",
            "l^1",
            "l^5"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "l^1",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following is scaled with length at l^1?",
        "options": [
            "Area",
            "Surface tension",
            "Resistance",
            "Moment of inertia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Resistance",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "When the radius of the pipe is scaled down proportionally,",
        "options": [
            "Volumetric Flow and pressure drop per unit length both increase",
            "Volumetric Flow decreases and pressure drop per unit length increases",
            "Volumetric Flow and pressure drop per unit length both decrease",
            "Volumetric Flow increases and pressure drop per unit length decreases"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Volumetric Flow decreases and pressure drop per unit length increases",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Main driving factor in scaling law is",
        "options": [
            "Weight to volume ratio",
            "Surface area to volume ratio",
            "Length to surface area ratio",
            "Surface finish to tolerance ratio"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Surface area to volume ratio",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is less effective at small scale",
        "options": [
            "Electrostatic forces",
            "Surface tension",
            "Inertial forces",
            "All the above",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Both (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Inertial forces",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "A square cantilever beam as shown in Figure below is scaled down proportionally (L and b) from 8 to 0.2. Maximum bending stress at the constraint",
        "options": [
            "Decreases 40 times",
            "Increases 40 times",
            "Decreases 1600 times",
            "Increases 1600 times"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Increases 1600 times",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "When the radius of the pipe is scaled down from 5 mm to 0.5 mm, rate of volumetric flow?",
        "options": [
            "Decreases 10 times",
            "Increases 10 times",
            "Increases 10000 times",
            "Decreases 10000 times"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Decreases 10000 times",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Small uncut chip thickness is responsible for",
        "options": [
            "High Cutting Temperature",
            "High Shear Yield Strength of workpiece",
            "Low friction coefficient",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (c)",
            "Only (b) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "High Shear Yield Strength of workpiece",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Size effect has influence on",
        "options": [
            "Chip Thickness",
            "Chip formation",
            "Cutting Force",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (c)",
            "Only (b) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 2,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In micro machining, generally the ratio of uncut chip thickness to cutting edge radius is",
        "options": [
            "Infinite",
            "Less than or equal to 1",
            "Very Large",
            "Zero"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Less than or equal to 1",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following step of failure of ductile material is shown in below figure?",
        "options": [
            "Inclusion",
            "Void growth",
            "Void Nucleation",
            "Necking between voids"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Necking between voids",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following material removal mechanism has significant effect on surface quality deterioration?",
        "options": [
            "Shearing",
            "Ploughing",
            "Rubbing",
            "Extrusion"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rubbing",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which plane of Silicon is the strongest?",
        "options": [
            "100",
            "110",
            "101",
            "111"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "111",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the unit of specific cutting energy?",
        "options": [
            "J/mm^3",
            "J/mm^2",
            "N/mm",
            "W/mm^3"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "J/mm^3",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Micro cutting of grains having different orientations would result in",
        "options": [
            "High fluctuation of cutting force",
            "Tool breakage",
            "High surface roughness",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (b)",
            "Only (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is minimum uncut chip thickness?",
        "options": [
            "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to avoid shearing of material during machining",
            "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to reduce the tool wear",
            "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to reduce built-up edge formation",
            "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to remove material in the form of chip"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to remove material in the form of chip",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one is the correct sequence of material removal mechanism with increase in the rake angle on negative side?",
        "options": [
            "Shearing  Extrusion  Ploughing  Rubbing",
            "Shearing Ploughing Extrusion Rubbing",
            "Shearing Rubbing Ploughing Extrusion",
            "Extrusion  Shearing  Ploughing  Rubbing"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shearing  Extrusion  Ploughing  Rubbing",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is not correct with reference to anisotropic material?",
        "options": [
            "Material properties are different in different planes",
            "Material properties are different in crystal orientations",
            "Force and energy required do not change when machining in different directions",
            "Shear stress is different in different planes and directions."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Force and energy required do not change when machining in different directions",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Match the following and choose correct option\nA Shearing I Displacement of material by plastic upheaval\nB Extrusion II Lowest rake angle on negative size\nC Ploughing III Significant friction force\nD Rubbing IV Similar to grinding",
        "options": [
            "A-III, B-IV, C- I, D-II",
            "A-IV, B-I, C- II, D-III",
            "A-II, B-IV, C- I, D-III",
            "A-II, B-I, C- IV, D-III"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A-II, B-IV, C- I, D-III",
        "week": 3,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the effect on cutting force in case of micro machining due to the reduction in uncut chip thickness?",
        "options": [
            "Increases proportionally",
            "Decreases proportionally",
            "Does not increase proportionally",
            "Does not decrease proportionally"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Does not decrease proportionally",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following problem is unlikely to occur due to burr formation?",
        "options": [
            "Improper part mating",
            "Accelerated device wear",
            "Decreased cost of production",
            "Decreased device performance"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Decreased cost of production",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following parameter is less responsible for burr formation?",
        "options": [
            "Cutting Speed",
            "Feed Rate",
            "Temperature",
            "Chip Thickness"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Temperature",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a deburring process?",
        "options": [
            "Ultrasonic wet peening",
            "Electrochemical polishing",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Cylindrical grinding",
            "Both (b) and (d)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a short frequency component?",
        "options": [
            "Waviness",
            "Profile",
            "Roughness",
            "Lay"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Roughness",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following instrument can be used for the surface roughness measurement of the complete region shown in below figure?",
        "options": [
            "Atomic Force Microscope",
            "Optical Microscope",
            "Stylus Method",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Both (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stylus Method",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct sequence of burr formation before crack propagation?",
        "options": [
            "Continuous cutting Pre-Initiation Initiation Pivoting Burr Development",
            "Pre-Initiation Initiation Continuous cutting  Pivoting Burr Development",
            "Continuous cutting Pivoting Pre-Initiation Initiation Burr Development",
            "Pivoting Continuous cutting  Pre-Initiation Initiation Burr Development"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Continuous cutting Pre-Initiation Initiation Pivoting Burr Development",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In the figure given below, size of the burrs will be more at the following location",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "3",
            "4"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "3",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following type of burr is shown in below figure?",
        "options": [
            "Tear Burr",
            "Cut-off Burr",
            "Rollover Burr",
            "Poisson Burr"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tear Burr",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the correct sequence of processes with reference to increase in the specific cutting energy",
        "options": [
            "Grinding  Micro machining  Conventional machining  Tensile testing",
            "Tensile testing  Micro machining  Conventional machining  Grinding",
            "Tensile testing  Conventional machining  Micro machining  Grinding",
            "Grinding  Micro machining  Tensile testing  Conventional machining"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tensile testing  Conventional machining  Micro machining  Grinding",
        "week": 4,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Elastic Recovery is dependent on",
        "options": [
            "Size of cutting edge radius",
            "Microstructure and hardness",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Neither (a) nor (b)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct about machining at micro scale?",
        "options": [
            "High specific cutting energy",
            "Difficulty in modeling",
            "Tool breakage",
            "Ease in sensing and monitoring"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ease in sensing and monitoring",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a moving body of a machine tool?",
        "options": [
            "Machine Base",
            "Column",
            "Spindle box housing",
            "Work tables"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Work tables",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The major design issue in the context of the design of the machine as a system is",
        "options": [
            "Structural Configuration",
            "Structural Connectivity",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Neither (a) nor (b)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The resolution of feedback encoder should be at least ______ than the machine controller?",
        "options": [
            "10 times lower",
            "10 times better",
            "100 times lower",
            "100 times better"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "10 times better",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about resolution?",
        "options": [
            "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n^2",
            "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of \u221an",
            "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n",
            "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n^n"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "A vacuum holder helps to,",
        "options": [
            "Evacuate the microchips by sucking it away time to time",
            "Hold the cutting fluid at the machining zone for a longer period",
            "Handle the micro components without making any permanent deformations",
            "Hold the tool monitoring systems at position for online monitoring"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Handle the micro components without making any permanent deformations",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the below cannot be used to monitor the machining process in real time?",
        "options": [
            "Dynamometer",
            "Touch probe",
            "Acoustic emission sensor",
            "Accelerometer"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Touch probe",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Bidirectional repeatability is difficult to achieve in axis movement due to",
        "options": [
            "Hysteresis of mechanical movement",
            "Linear movement of drive",
            "Low accuracy of the slide movement",
            "Low resolution of the slide movement"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hysteresis of mechanical movement",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is resolution with reference to terms of machine tool?",
        "options": [
            "The least variation in the dimensions of the machined component and the desired value.",
            "How fast the tool or workpiece can reach to the desired location during command execution.",
            "The least increment of movement, the machine is capable to produce.",
            "It is related to the tolerance of the machined component."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The least increment of movement, the machine is capable to produce.",
        "week": 5,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about closed loop structure?",
        "options": [
            "Good thermal stability",
            "Easy access to work zone",
            "Strong ridged structural loop",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (b)",
            "Only (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "CMM stands for",
        "options": [
            "Co-ordinate Machine Measurement",
            "Centre Measuring Machine",
            "Co-ordinate Measuring Machine",
            "Centre Machine Measurement"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Co-ordinate Measuring Machine",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct match of the numbers marked on the figure given below?",
        "options": [
            "1-Leading Edge 2-Stagnant Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
            "1- Stagnant Edge 2- Leading Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
            "1-Leading Edge 2- Bleeding Edge 3- Stagnant Edge",
            "1- Bleeding Edge 2- Leading Edge 3- Stagnant Edge"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "1- Stagnant Edge 2- Leading Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The sensitive directions in case of Milling Machine are",
        "options": [
            "X-axis and Y-axis",
            "X-axis and Z-axis",
            "Y-axis and Z-axis",
            "X-axis, Y-axis and Z-axis"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "X-axis, Y-axis and Z-axis",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the different components of error in a linear movement?",
        "options": [
            "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 2 roll error and 1 tilt error",
            "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error",
            "2 position error, 1 straightness error, 2 roll error and 1 tilt error",
            "2 position error, 1 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The degree of freedom for bolt and nut combination is",
        "options": [
            "Translation and Rotation (Independent)",
            "Only translation",
            "Only rotation",
            "Translation and Rotation (Coupled)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Translation and Rotation (Coupled)",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "When travelling in X- direction, Flatness can be defined as",
        "options": [
            "Displacement error along the X-axis",
            "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
            "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Both (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Kinematic errors are not related to",
        "options": [
            "Imperfect Geometry",
            "Alignment and dimension of the machine tools",
            "Wear or material aging",
            "Range of the spindle speed"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Range of the spindle speed",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "When travelling in X- direction, Straightness can be defined as",
        "options": [
            "Displacement error along the X-axis",
            "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
            "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Both (a) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Drift error in the machine tool is due to",
        "options": [
            "Aging of the components",
            "Improper mating of the components",
            "Thermal expansion of the components",
            "Failure of the components"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Aging of the components",
        "week": 6,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a preferable material for making structure of micro machine tool?",
        "options": [
            "Metal",
            "Granite",
            "Ceramic",
            "Polymer concrete"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Polymer concrete",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the least important material property of the machine frame?",
        "options": [
            "Young\u2019s modulus",
            "Shear modulus",
            "Poisson\u2019s ratio",
            "Thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Poisson\u2019s ratio",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Increasing order of Young\u2019s modulus of different material which are used for making machine structure is:",
        "options": [
            "Elastomers<Non-technical ceramics<Technical ceramics< Polymers",
            "Elastomers<Technical ceramics<Non-technical ceramics< Polymers",
            "Elastomers<Polymers<Composite<Technical ceramics",
            "Elastomers< Polymers < Technical ceramics< Non-technical ceramics"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Elastomers<Polymers<Composite<Technical ceramics",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Specific energy requirement for making the high strength material will be",
        "options": [
            "Low",
            "High",
            "In between low and high",
            "Specific energy requirement is not the criteria for making high strength material"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "High",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What you will do to reduce the local strain in the component?",
        "options": [
            "Reduce thickness of the wall",
            "Increase thickness of the wall",
            "Reduce the weight of the component",
            "Increase the weight of the component"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Increase thickness of the wall",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following statement is true?",
        "options": [
            "Polymer concrete is heavier than C.I.",
            "C.I. has better thermal stability than Polymer concrete",
            "Polymer concrete has superior dynamic and static rigidity",
            "C.I. has better damping capacity than Polymer concrete"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Polymer concrete has superior dynamic and static rigidity",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Axis of the guideways should have",
        "options": [
            "Low velocity as well as stiff bearing",
            "High velocity as well as stiff bearing",
            "High acceleration as well as stiff bearing",
            "Low acceleration as well as stiff bearing"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "High acceleration as well as stiff bearing",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the drawback of the granite when it is used for making machine tool?",
        "options": [
            "Low damping",
            "Low wear resistance",
            "Moisture absorbing capacity",
            "Presence of residual stress"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Moisture absorbing capacity",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following guideways is more preferable for taking load in up-down as well as left-right directions?",
        "options": [
            "Hydrostatic",
            "Hydrodynamics",
            "Linear",
            "Box"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Linear",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Basic static load rating of the roller is roughly defined as:",
        "options": [
            "Total permanent deformation is the half of the diameter of the roller",
            "Total permanent deformation is 1/1000 of the diameter of the roller",
            "Total permanent deformation is 1/10000 of the diameter of the roller",
            "Total permanent deformation is 1/100000 of the diameter of the roller"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Total permanent deformation is 1/10000 of the diameter of the roller",
        "week": 7,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The function of precision laser system in MMC is to determine",
        "options": [
            "Only diameter of the tool",
            "Only length of the tool",
            "Both diameter and length of the tool",
            "Rake and clearance angle of the tool"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Both diameter and length of the tool",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following factors affect air bearing life the most?",
        "options": [
            "Speed of rotation",
            "External load",
            "Acceleration",
            "Cleanliness of air"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cleanliness of air",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Mode of failure of air bearing",
        "options": [
            "Spalling wear",
            "Smearing wear",
            "Erosion wear",
            "Fretting wear"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Erosion wear",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The variation of radial stiffness of air bearing with respect to shaft angular position is",
        "options": [
            "Non uniform",
            "Uniform",
            "Triangular",
            "Trapezium"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Uniform",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following bearing offers the highest friction & has the lowest cost?",
        "options": [
            "Air bearing",
            "Hydrostatic bearing",
            "Roller bearing",
            "Cylindrical bearing"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Roller bearing",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "On which part of the linear motor magnet is present?",
        "options": [
            "Rotor",
            "Stator",
            "Forcer",
            "Coil"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stator",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The maximum speed of a linear motor is governed by",
        "options": [
            "Bus voltage",
            "Speed of the control electronics",
            "Resolution",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The stiffness of the linear motor does not depend upon",
        "options": [
            "Peak force of the motor",
            "Resolution of the feedback",
            "Current available",
            "Speed of the travel"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Speed of the travel",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The problem of heating in the linear drive is due to",
        "options": [
            "Thermal heating",
            "Mechanical friction",
            "Both of the above",
            "Electrical power supply"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Electrical power supply",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is/are true for MMC (Micro Machining Center)?",
        "options": [
            "It has high moisture retention capacity and low damping coefficient",
            "It has high moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient",
            "It has low moisture retention capacity and low damping coefficient",
            "It has low moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It has low moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient",
        "week": 8,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is 4 in 4 Bit encoder?",
        "options": [
            "It has 4 LEDs",
            "It has 4 transmitters",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "It has 4 tracks"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It has 4 tracks",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following components or mechanisms is not the part of the belt driven spindle?",
        "options": [
            "Tooling system",
            "Drawbar mechanism",
            "Tool release system",
            "Linear encoder"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Linear encoder",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Spindle bearing should not provide",
        "options": [
            "High rotational speed",
            "Low transfer torque",
            "High power to the cutting tool",
            "Reasonable loading"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Low transfer torque",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
        "options": [
            "Angular contact bearing provide precision",
            "Tapered bearing is used for high load application",
            "Both (a) and (b)",
            "Tapered bearing has lower stiffness over ball bearings"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following bearing is highly accurate and used in high speed spindle?",
        "options": [
            "ABEC 1",
            "ABEC 5",
            "ABEC 7",
            "ABEC 9"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "ABEC 9",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
        "options": [
            "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have high contact angle",
            "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle",
            "To have greater bending load carrying capacity bearing should have high contact angle",
            "To have greater axial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
        "options": [
            "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in drilling",
            "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in milling",
            "High contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in shaping",
            "High contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in planning"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in milling",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the importance of the bearing preloading?",
        "options": [
            "To provide excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing",
            "To remove excess play by applying more friction to a bearing",
            "To provide excess play by applying radial and thrust forces to a bearing",
            "To remove excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To remove excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Excessive preloading of the bearing doesn\u2019t result in",
        "options": [
            "Increased heat generation",
            "Excessive stress",
            "Higher chances of fatigue",
            "Decreased torque"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Decreased torque",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the purpose(s) of duplex bearing?",
        "options": [
            "To provide high rotational speed",
            "To provide high feed rate during machining",
            "To provide less friction",
            "To provide load sharing and high stiffness"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To provide load sharing and high stiffness",
        "week": 9,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Races and ball in ball bearing are made up of which of the following material?",
        "options": [
            "Ceramic",
            "Carbide",
            "Steel",
            "Cast iron"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Steel",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the mechanisms of the bearing failure is",
        "options": [
            "Hot welding of raceway material to the ball",
            "Cold welding of ball material to the raceway",
            "Hot welding between balls",
            "Cold welding between balls"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cold welding of ball material to the raceway",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Air bearing spindle provides",
        "options": [
            "Low torque, low speed",
            "High speed, high torque",
            "High torque, low speed",
            "High speed, low torque"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "High speed, low torque",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "How you will reduce the warping of the aerostatic spindle?",
        "options": [
            "Increase temperature gradient in the spindle",
            "Decrease temperature gradient in the spindle",
            "Increase pressure gradient in the spindle",
            "Decrease pressure gradient in the spindle"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Decrease temperature gradient in the spindle",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following tool retention system is best for high speed application?",
        "options": [
            "HSK",
            "BT",
            "ISO",
            "CAT"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "HSK",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of 3 surface contact holder of tool retention system?",
        "options": [
            "High speed",
            "High dynamic stiffness",
            "High static stiffness",
            "High runout"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "High runout",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a micro tool fabrication process?",
        "options": [
            "Electro Discharge Machining (EDM)",
            "Focused Ion Beam (FIB) Machining",
            "Abrasive jet machining (AJM)",
            "Laser Beam Machining (LBM)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Abrasive jet machining (AJM)",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In micro-tool fabrication by Wire Electric Discharge Grinding (WEDG)",
        "options": [
            "Wire is made of aluminum and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
            "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of ceramic",
            "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
            "Wire is made of aluminum and electrode is of ceramic"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "ELID process uses",
        "options": [
            "In-process dressing of the grinding wheel to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
            "In-process monitoring of the status of the abrasive particles",
            "In-process dressing of the copper electrode (cathode) to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
            "In-process monitoring of the forces acting on the workpiece"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In-process dressing of the grinding wheel to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Micro tools having diameter less than 50 \u00b5m generally fabricated without helix angle",
        "options": [
            "To reduce the wastage of the material in the form of chips during fabrication",
            "To improve the surface finish on the machined component",
            "To improve their rigidity",
            "To reduce burr formation"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To improve their rigidity",
        "week": 10,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is true?",
        "options": [
            "HSS cutter is harder than carbide cutter",
            "HSS cutter can bend more than carbide cutter",
            "HSS cutter has long life than carbide cutter under the same operating conditions",
            "HSS cutter does not required coolant during machining operation"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "HSS cutter can bend more than carbide cutter",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the major issue of tool breakage in micro machining?",
        "options": [
            "Chip clogging",
            "Higher rotational speed",
            "Small depth of cut",
            "Low feed rate"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chip clogging",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Hammering vibration is produce when using",
        "options": [
            "End mill cutter without coating",
            "End mill cutter with axial runout",
            "Two flutes end mill cutter",
            "Four flutes end mill cutter"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Two flutes end mill cutter",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the problem in using small machine tool for micro machining applications?",
        "options": [
            "Small machine tools are costly",
            "It is difficult to get small size sensors and actuators for monitoring and control of the small machine tool",
            "It is difficult to make and assemble components while building the small machine tool",
            "It is difficult to learn the machining operation in small size machine tool"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It is difficult to get small size sensors and actuators for monitoring and control of the small machine tool",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In diamond turning,",
        "options": [
            "X and Z movement is given by the cutting tool",
            "X and Z movement is given by the spindle head",
            "X movement is given by the cutting tool and Z movement is given by the spindle head",
            "X movement is given by the spindle head and Z movement is given by the cutting tool"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "X movement is given by the spindle head and Z movement is given by the cutting tool",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "The diamond turning can be classified as facing and fly cutting based on the",
        "options": [
            "Number of axis",
            "Type of coordinate system",
            "Type of machining operation",
            "Type of tooling system"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Type of machining operation",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In micromachining, generally an end mill cutter having _____ flutes are used.",
        "options": [
            "2",
            "3",
            "4",
            "5"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "2",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Built up edge in micro milling",
        "options": [
            "Decreases surface finish",
            "Increases deflection",
            "Increases material removal rate",
            "Increases tool life"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Increases deflection",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Diamond turning is generally used for finishing of",
        "options": [
            "Cast iron",
            "Mild steel",
            "Copper",
            "Tungsten carbide"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Copper",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Two axes with T slide is associated with",
        "options": [
            "X-Z axis diamond turning machine",
            "R-\u03f4 axis diamond turning machine",
            "X-Y axis diamond turning machine",
            "Y-Z axis diamond turning machine"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "X-Z axis diamond turning machine",
        "week": 11,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In ultra-precision machining, surface finish (Ra) is typically in the range of",
        "options": [
            "<10\u00b5m",
            ">10 \u00b5m",
            "<20nm",
            ">20nm"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "<20nm",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Depth of cut (uncut chip thickness) in ultra-precision machining is in the range of",
        "options": [
            "1-10 \u00b5m",
            "10-100 \u00b5m",
            "0.1-10 \u00b5m",
            "0.01-0.1 \u00b5m"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "0.1-10 \u00b5m",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Material removal rate in the soft loop finishing technique depends on",
        "options": [
            "Pressure",
            "Velocity",
            "Preston coefficient",
            "All of the above",
            "Only (a) and (c)",
            "Only (b) and (c)"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following cannot be measured by the tool setting device?",
        "options": [
            "X-Z offset of the cutting tool",
            "Tool nose radius",
            "Position of the center of the nose radius",
            "Waviness of the cutting edge"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Waviness of the cutting edge",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "When machining of concave surface by diamond turning using large nose radius,",
        "options": [
            "Small cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
            "Long cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
            "Workpiece needs to be rotated at high speed",
            "Workpiece needs to be rotated at low speed"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Long cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Tool with small nose radius can be used for machining of",
        "options": [
            "External feature",
            "Fragile workpiece",
            "Hard material",
            "Composite"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fragile workpiece",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In diamond turning, workpiece is gripped by",
        "options": [
            "3 jaws chuck",
            "4 jaws chuck",
            "Vacuum chuck",
            "Self-centric chuck"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vacuum chuck",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the sequence of basic composition of a sensing system?",
        "options": [
            "Transform -- Sensor -- Signal processing -- Decision making",
            "Sensor -- Transform -- Decision making -- Signal processing",
            "Transform -- Sensor -- Decision making -- Signal processing",
            "Sensor -- Transform -- Signal processing -- Decision making"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sensor -- Transform -- Signal processing -- Decision making",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "In which case, the amplitude of AE signal will be high?",
        "options": [
            "Crack propagation",
            "Isotropy",
            "Plastic deformation",
            "Ductile failure"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Crack propagation",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following instrument has very high precision level (<1 nm)",
        "options": [
            "Accelerometer",
            "Encoders",
            "Acoustic emission",
            "Load cells"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Acoustic emission",
        "week": 12,
        "year": 2025
    }
]